(upbeat music)
- Low English learners,
welcome back to English Pod.
My name is Marco.
- And I'm Erica.
- And today we have a
special lesson for all of you
who are looking for a
new apartment or house.
- Or even if you're not looking for
an apartment, this lesson will be useful
because it can help you describe what
your current apartment or house looks like.
- That's right.
So we're gonna be describing an apartment
and other vocabulary
related to apartment hunting.
Why don't we take a
look at some of the first
words that we have
in vocabulary preview?
- Very vocabulary preview.
We're gonna hear these
two words in the dialogue.
The first one is Landlord.
- Landlord.
- All right, so who is a
landlord or what is a landlord?
- What's pretty simple, a landlord
is the person who owns the house.
- Okay.
- Or apartment.
So the owner of the house.
- Right.
And a landlord rents out
the apartment to the tenants.
- Okay, very good tenants.
- Tenants.
- So the tenants are the people that
are renting the apartment or house.
- Exactly.
- Two important words that we'll find
in the dialogue, tenants and landlord.
- So why don't we take a
listen to the dialogue now and
we'll hear as a couple is
checking out a new apartment.
(upbeat music)
- Hi, we are the Christiansons.
We're here to see the apartment.
- Oh hi, short, come on in.
Well, as you can see, the place has
just been renovated, the previous tenants
left a huge messier.
So the landlord has done everything.
- It looks great.
It's so bright and airy.
What great light.
I really love these hardwood floors.
What's the square footage of this place?
- Well, it's about 120 square meters
or 1300 square feet, more or less.
Oh, the landlord has also
installed new kitchen appliances.
There's a new dishwasher and
a professional grade gas range.
Really at this price, this
place is an amazing deal.
- I love it.
But wait, what are the payment terms?
- First and last month rent as the deposit
and rent is due on
the first of every month.
Considering the amount of money invested
into the apartment, it's a very good deal.
- Yes, it is.
Too good to be true.
- The living room and dining room
are quite spacious as you can see.
And down this hall,
here's a master bedroom.
It is a huge walking closet
and an end-sweet bathroom.
We can't go in there yet as the police, I
mean, the cleanup crew hasn't finished yet.
- Oh, what do you mean?
What's in here?
(dramatic music)
(screaming)
(upbeat music)
- All right, so apparently the
apartment was too good to be true.
- Yeah, I don't think that's exactly what
they are expecting to find in the bathroom.
- Exactly, well, we did find a
lot of great words and phrases.
So why don't we take a look at
that now in language takeaway?
- Language takeaway.
We're just gonna look
at a bunch of vocabulary
items related to apartments
and house huntings.
So we've got a lot to cover here.
So let's get started with
the first one, renovated.
- Renovated.
- Renovated, right?
So in the apartment was newly renovated.
- Okay, so the verb to renovate.
Great word and I think some examples
will help us understand the meaning.
- Example one.
I had to renovate my kitchen because I
accidentally burned everything while cooking.
- Example two.
- The city recently renovated
the ceiling of the local church.
- Example three.
- John is planning on renovating his
nightclub so as to make it more modern.
- Okay, so basically two renovate
means to make new again.
- Right, when you renovate
a house or an apartment
you take everything down
and build the backup again.
- Okay, so it's usually
only used for buildings
for apartments, for
houses, or offices.
- You don't say you renovate your computer.
- Yeah, and also when you
just do something really simple,
like change the paint
color, that's not a renovation.
- Okay.
- That's redecoration.
When you renovate, you have to like,
use a hammer and saw and lots of tools.
- Change, yeah.
- Okay, so the apartment was newly
renovated and it was bright and airy.
- Airy.
- All right, so airy, well I guess
we understand the word air.
- Yeah.
- So if an apartment or something is airy.
- It has lots of space, lots
of place to move around.
- Okay, so it's wide, it's open.
- It's open, okay.
- Yeah, an open apartment.
Very good.
Now for our next word, an important
question she asked for the square footage.
Square footage, the square
footage of the apartment.
Okay, so we know square foot, right?
So feet like a measure of space.
- Right.
- The square footage is just
basically the area, how big?
- Okay, so why don't we listen
to some examples of how we
can use these two words,
square footage, in a sentence.
- Example one.
As a civil engineer, I have to calculate
the square footage of the construction site.
- Example two.
- Robert is worried that the square
footage of this land is not big enough.
- Example three.
- If you multiply the width of the room,
by the length you will have
the square footage of the room.
- Those are some great examples.
And I find this, the ending of this word,
edge footage, it's interesting, isn't it?
- Yeah, I guess you can only
use it with the imperial system.
So you can also say, tonnage, right?
So how big, how heavy, or mileage.
- Mileage, right?
But you can't say, for example, in
meters, you wouldn't say meter age.
- No, you can't say that, right?
So it's not for the metric system,
it's only for some units of
measurement in the imperial system.
- Exactly.
- All right, so after we've
measured the square footage
of the apartment, we saw
that they had new appliances.
- Appliances, appliances.
- Appliances.
- So kitchen appliances, what are those?
- Machines that do stuff in the kitchen.
- All right, so a blender,
a stove, a microwave.
- Yep.
- Or I can say electric appliances.
- So like your TV, an iron vacuum cleaner.
- Okay, so appliance can
be any type of machine
that's used in a house.
- In a house.
- Yeah, and well, one of these appliances
was a professional grade gas range.
- Okay, this is a great phrase,
and I wanna break it down.
So a gas range.
Now this is basically a stove, okay?
That uses gas instead of electricity.
- So I can have an electric range.
- Exactly.
Now professional grades, this is
something that's really high quality.
- So if it's high quality, why do
we say it's professional grade?
- 'Cause it's so good
that professionals use it.
- Okay, so can I only have
professional grade kitchen appliances?
- No, of course not, you
can have a professional grade
anything, like a professional
grade carpet, for example.
- Okay, or a professional
grade pickup truck.
- Or you can even change this a
little bit and say industrial grade.
So after we've seen all the appliances,
they describe the house
as spacious, spacious.
The house is very spacious.
- Pretty easy, we know
the word space here, right?
- Right.
- So obviously this means lots of space.
- It has lots of space.
So I guess maybe spacious
and area a little bit similar, right?
- Yeah.
- Okay, and of course
once we were in the master
bedroom, we saw that
they had a walk-in closet.
- A walk-in closet.
- Walk-in closet.
- A walk-in closet, right?
So this is very easy, I guess.
Walk-in, you can walk into it, right?
And so it's a huge closet, right?
- Yeah, it's, now just a
note on the spelling here.
Walk-in are hyphenated.
- Okay, walk-in closet, very good.
And apart from this beautiful
closet, we had an on-sweet bathroom.
- On-sweet bathroom, on-sweet bathroom.
- For another note on
the spelling here, it's EN.
- Right.
It's an SU-I-T-E.
- So even though it's EN,
we pronounce it like an O-N.
- Yep.
- On-sweet.
- So an on-sweet bathroom
is a bathroom inside the room.
- Okay, inside the master bedroom.
- Mm-hmm.
- Very good.
On-sweet bathroom.
So a lot of great
words describing the
apartment and also
other aspects of real estate.
- So why don't we listen to
these one more time in context
and we'll see how they fit
together to describe an apartment.
(upbeat music)
Hi, we are the Christiansons.
We're here to see the apartment.
- Oh, hi, short, come on in.
Well, as you can see, the
place has just been renovated.
The previous tenants left a huge messier
so the landlord has done everything.
- It looks great.
It's so bright and airy.
What great light.
I really love these hardwood floors.
What's the square footage of this place?
- Well, it's about 120 square meters
or 1300 square feet more or less.
Oh, the landlord has also
installed new kitchen appliances.
There's a new dishwasher and
a professional grade gas range.
Really at this price, this
place is an amazing deal.
- I love it.
But wait, what are the payment terms?
- First and last month rent as deposit and
rent is due on the first of every month.
Considering the amount of money invested
into the apartment, it's a very good deal.
- Yes, it is.
- It's too good to be true.
The living room and dining room
are quite spacious as you can see.
And down this hall,
here's a master bedroom.
It has a huge walking closet
and an end-sweet bathroom.
We can't go in there yet as the place I
mean, the clean-up crew hasn't finished yet.
- Oh, what do you mean?
What's in here?
(dramatic music)
- Hey!
(screaming)
- All right, so this is
always kind of difficult
to look for a new apartment
and to go and see them.
But it's interesting here, they were
renting and they had a real estate agent.
- Yeah, and actually this is very
uncommon in America, isn't it?
- Yeah, I guess you don't
really use a real estate agent
unless you're going to
buy a house or apartment.
So when you're renting, you
just go and look by yourself.
- Right, you can find ads in the newspaper,
on the internet, and deal
directly with the landlord.
- Right, so after you've
done your house hunting
and found your apartment, you
gotta set up the payment conditions.
- Right, like we saw in the dialogue,
the payment terms were
first and last month's rent
as deposit, so that's
basically they'll keep
that just in case you damage
something in the apartment.
- Or have a monster
living in your bathroom.
- Exactly.
And another thing is that I've noticed in
some countries you pay rent in advance.
- Right, so in America, you only
pay one month's rent at a time, right?
So I guess this is an
interesting topic, real estate
and apartment hunting and renting
is different in different countries.
So that's where you guys need to come and
tell us how does this work in your country?
- You can also use
some of the vocabulary in
this dialogue to tell us
about your apartments.
- Right, how many rooms do you have?
- Bad rooms, dining rooms.
- What's the square footage?
- Exactly, or how many
square meters, right?
- Yep, so check out
our website, EnglishPod.
com.
- All right, and we'll see you guys there.
- Thanks for listening, and
until next time, goodbye.
(upbeat music)